you know, so we we had this hot war with
Pakistan uh in May and it happened and
the the nuclear question came up again
and I thought what better person than
you to sort of you know illuminate a
little bit more about Pakistan's nuclear
weapons and everything. So you were
there on the ground in Pakistan in 2002
2003 we also saw Pakistan sort of lurch
into almost like a civil war with the
various terrorists it had propped up in
its backyard. You know, was there ever a
fear that these nuclear weapons would
fall into a terrorist hands?
>> Yes. When I was when I was stationed in
Pakistan in 2002, I was told
unofficially
that that the Pentagon controlled the
Pakistani nuclear arsenal, that Musharif
had turned control over to the United
States because he was afraid of exactly
what you just described.
But the Pakistanis in the intervening
years and remember I was there 23
years ago over the last 23 years the
Pakistanis have come to say that is
absolutely not true. The United States
has nothing to do with the Pakistani
nuclear arsenal that Pakistani generals
are the ones that control it. So I don't
know if if that's true
then I would be very worried about who
is in charge politically in Pakistan.
>> You know for example for example um Iran
Khan I can't believe that I forgot his
name.
>> Who's in jail? A popular in jail.
>> Yes. Yeah.
>> Right. And still wildly popular.
>> Wildly. Yeah. He told us when he was
still the prime minister, he said,
"Listen, I've got this political
situation here domestically, I'm going
to start blaming you for everything."
And and the ambassador laughed and said,
"We get blamed for everything anyway, so
we don't care." So everything that
happened, it was the United States
fault, and it was the US, they turned
their backs on us, and the US did this,
and the US did that, and then they
arrested him anyway.
So he got a message out to the US
government saying can you help me get
out of this and we went to Jamaima
Goldmid his gold whatever her name was
ex-wife
>> and she went to Pakistan and asked them
if they would release him and they said
no.
So like you, I'm worried about continued
disagreement in Pakistani politics that
has the potential to spill into the
streets because the Pakistanis have a
tendency to get themselves spun up
>> and people die during demonstrations and
there are attacks against political
figures and assassinations and and uh
and the country is not known for its uh
transformative, you know, leaders making
positive decisions. I'll tell you
another thing. When Benazer BH was in
exile in uh Dubai,
>> um I went to see her with another a
senior officer, I went as the notetaker
and um she lived in this
$5 million
palace on the on the Gulf.
And we were sitting in the the front
room, the the salon of of the house, and
we heard a car pull up
and she said
her exact words, "So help me God. If he
came home with another Bentley, I'm
going to kill him."
>> Is her daddy?
>> Yeah.
>> Her husband.
>> And I said to my boss afterwards,
"She makes $60,000 a year. She lives in
a $5 million house and he has a
collection of Bentleys.
Aren't they ashamed of themselves? Like,
how can they go back to Pakistan and
look the Pakistani people in the face
when their people don't even have shoes
and enough food to eat? Like I
understand corruption is a problem
there, but that level of corruption.
>> Yeah.
>> Come on. Well, those are the kinds of
politicians that the Pakistani people
have to deal with.
>> You know, in this uh war that happened
in May, India for the first time
escalated it to a level where we had
cruise missiles flying into uh Pakistan
with direct hits uh at the time. Um
>> and the from the Indian side this
constant uh line is is said right from
the prime minister level up. He says
that uh that we called their nuclear
bluffs.
You said that you were told unofficially
that you knew that America knew where
the nukes were. Do you think Americans
told India that the control of Pakistani
nukes also uh lies with America? I doubt
it.
Um, I doubt it because of the
viciferousness with which the Pakistanis
have come out publicly and said that
they control the nukes. But I can tell
you definitively
>> that the State Department was telling
both sides, if you're going to fight,
fight. Keep it short and keep it
non-nuclear.
If nuclear weapons are introduced, the
whole world is going to change. And so I
think there was restraint on both sides.
The Pakistanis need to come to a policy
conclusion that there's nothing positive
for them in fighting India. Nothing,
literally nothing good will come of a of
an actual war between India and Pakistan
because the Pakistanis will lose.
>> Mhm.
>> It's as simple as that. They'll lose.
And I'm not talking about nuclear
weapons. I'm talking just about a
conventional war. The Pakistanis will
lose.
>> Right. And so there's no benefit to
constantly provoking the Indians.
>> Right? Last question on the nuclear
issue. I promise I'll move on after
that. Okay, let's nx the control part.
you you doubt that the actual control,
but there was a New York Times article
written by the by the New York Times
editor at that time for national
security that uh that President Bush had
folded in hundreds of millions of
dollars in grants uh to Pakistan to
safeguard their nuclear assets. The New
York Times knew about this program but
decided to sit on it for a number of
months before they finally published it.
So even if they don't control it, did
they give technology to safeguard it?
>> Most likely. Yes.
>> What would that be?
>> Andy, that I don't know. I I it's not my
area of expertise. I I couldn't
speculate. But I will tell you that
the fact that the New York Times sat on
the article
is a way of confirming its truth. M
>> and what I mean is when one of the big
outlets, the New York Times, the
Washington Post, the Wall Street
Journal, you know, the Los Angeles Times
or one of the big broadcast news
networks, um when they come across
information like this that's really it's
big and it involves classified
information,
they always ask the White House to
confirm or to deny
>> if the information is truly classified
and it's sensitive.
The national security adviser will ask
for a meeting. Sometimes the meeting is
with the president and the head of the
newspaper. Usually it's the national
security adviser. and they'll say,
"Look,
yes, it's true, but it's so sensitive
that if you publish it, it will put
lives in danger.
Almost always, they'll sit on the
article until enough time passes that
people aren't in danger anymore. The
fact that they sat on the article is
confirmation that it was true." M
>> just a couple of months later in March
of 2002, we raided a Lashkar Itaya safe
house in Lahore.
>> Okay. And
>> and in that house, we captured three
Lashkar Itayaba fighters who had with
them a copy of the al-Qaeda training
manual.
And it was the first time
analytically that we were able to
connect Lashkaraya with al-Qaeda. The
very first time I remember receiving a
cable from the from the deputy director
of the CIA for intelligence
congratulating us on finding this
training manual saying it was the very
first time that we could attach the
Pakistani government
to al-Qaeda. What stopped you from going
after Pakistan then? You you have the
first smoking gun of a inextricably
linked ISI because the le or the JM jud
the various names that they come up with
essentially ISI proxies propped up by
the Pakistani government and now they
have a direct correct
>> yes
>> why why didn't you ever bring this up
>> that was the decision that was made at
the white house
>> and the decision was that that the
relationship is bigger than India
Pakistan
at least temporarily the relationship
we needed the Pakistanis actually more
than they needed us at that point we
were happy to throw money at them that's
what they responded to
>> but we really needed them to let us base
our drones in Baluchistan for example um
have what's called a picket line CIA
officers all the way up and down the
border with uh with Afghanistan
So, so from Wazinistan all the way down
to Baluchistan to
>> Baluchistan.
>> Mhm.
>> We we needed a presence in Pashaw. We
needed a presence in Queda. We needed a
presence in Karachi and Lahore. And we
needed for them to say yes to everything
that we wanted to do. And so a decision
was made at the White House that if we
strategically ignore
this terrorism problem visa v India
the relationship would be much easier to
negotiate and and so that's what we did.
I'll tell you one other thing years
later in 2008
>> um I had I had left the CIA. I had blown
the whistle already and I was working as
a as a uh counterterrorism advisor to
ABC News, one of the big news networks
here in the United States.
>> And um
and uh I got a call saying, "Are you
watching the news?" I said, "No, it was
the night before Thanksgiving, so it's a
major American holiday. Major holiday."
I said, "No, I I'm I'm not watching the
news. Uh there's been a an enormous
terrorist attack in Mumbai. They're
attacking hotels. They're attacking
Jewish centers. They're attacking this
and attacking that." I said, "Oh my
god." They said, "Um,
can you come into the studio and talk
about this?" I said, "Of course."
Everybody else was on vacation because
it's the eve of a major holiday.
>> Yes. So, I jump in the shower, I shave,
and as I'm getting dressed, my wife, who
was still in the CIA at the time, she
said, "You should watch, while you're
getting dressed, you should watch what
the other networks are saying about
this." So, I I go to CNN, they said,
"Alqaeda." I go to Fox, al-Qaeda, MSNBC,
it's al-Qaeda. And these are all friends
of mine who were saying it. And I said
to my wife, I don't think this is
al-Qaeda.
She said,
"Wow, you better really be sure of
yourself if you're going to put your
reputation on the line and tell the
entire country that this is not
al-Qaeda." So, I I drove down to ABC
News to the studio.
>> Mhm.
>> And they wired me up and I was talking
to the reporter in New York and I said,
"Listen, I don't think this is al-Qaeda.
I think this is this is the Pakistani
uh supported Kashmir groups." I said,
'Ala doesn't care about India. They
don't have any problem with the Indians.
Their fight is with us.
>> Yes.
>> And he said, 'Oh my god. He said, you
should You're going to need to be 100%
sure because everybody is saying it's
al-Qaeda. And I said, I I was in the CIA
long enough that I can say that I feel
strongly this is not al-Qaeda. And so I
went on the air and I was the only
person that said I believe that these
are Pakistani Kashmir separatist groups
supported by the Pakistani ISI.
>> Right?
>> And that turned out to be exactly the
case
>> to the point where ABC News made
television commercials saying ABC News
the Mumbai attacks we were the only ones
that got it right. Right. But there was
a bigger issue here, bigger story here.
And the story was that Pakistan was
committing terrorism in India
>> and nobody did anything about it.
>> [music]